# 哈喽 大家好
Hello guys,
# 我伯爷他从自己家里面搜了一包红茶茶叶出来
My uncle found a bag of black tea at his house.
# 这是好久的茶叶哦
How long have you put it?
# 这包茶叶放在我的柜子里头我放忘记了
I've put it in the drawer and forgot about it.
# 不晓得好久还有包茶叶
Don’t know how long there’s still a bag of tea.
# 都三四年这包茶叶 不晓得发没发霉都不晓得
For about three or four years, I’m not sure if it gets moldy or not.
# 没有发霉 这个茶叶放了几年
It’s not moldy. Although it’s been so long,
# 应该是这个保存得好
it got well saved.
# 这个包装好
The package is good.
# 嗯 这个包装不容易坏
The package helps it to last longer.
# 搞忘记了
I forgot about it.
# 被遗忘的茶叶
A forgotten tea.
# 今天我们用这个遗忘的茶叶来煮一碗这个茶叶蛋
Today, we are going to use this forgotten tea to make tea eggs.
# 然后今天我还准备了一个特殊的东西
I prepared something special for today.
# 加点可乐进去煮
I will put some coke to boil.
# 吃过没有四伯爷
Have you tried it, uncle?
# 没有
Nope.
# 我相信你吃过茶叶蛋
I know you have tea eggs before.
# 茶叶蛋我是吃过
I had tea eggs.
# 可乐茶叶蛋你没吃过噶
You never tried coke tea egg, though.
# 没有没有
NO no no.
# 好
Okay.
# 那就准备哈这个
Let’s prepare for this,
# 我们煮这个茶叶蛋 大家都是用铁锅进去煮
People usually use an iron pot to boil the tea egg.
# 其实做茶叶蛋最好是用这个电饭锅
Actually, the best way is to use an instant pot.
# 电饭锅做出来的茶叶蛋
The tea egg cooked by instant pot is,
# 因为它这个火力是比较均匀
the heats are more equal;
# 慢慢煮的 更加的入味
slowly boiled, more flavor penetrated.
# 好 拿到那边去煮
Okay, put it there to boil.
# 我先把它煮熟
We hard boil it first.
# 好
Right.
# 我先把蛋弄来煮了哈
I boil the egg first.
# 要的
Yes,
# 这个水刚好没过鸡蛋就可以了
We need enough water to slightly cover the egg.
# 等下我们的茶叶要用
We are going to use the tea...
# 你经常喝茶 你第一道茶是丢了的噶
You drink tea a lot, Do you drink the first drink?
# 第一道茶反正没得嫩好喝得
The first drink doesn’t taste good.
# 有点苦
It’s bitter.
# 二开茶是最安逸的
The second drink is the most tasteful.
# 所以我们用茶叶也同样的道理
So we are going to make this tea the same way,
# 用第二泡来放进去煮
using the second drink.
# 就是第一下放水
# 头一开茶
Throw the water
# 那个水不要
you put at the first.
# 没得好好喝得
It’s not tasty.
# 还有一个茶叶蛋不能多吃四伯爷
One more thing, don’t eat too much tea eggs, uncle.
# 我少吃这个东西
I need to have it less.
# 嗯 是
Right.
# 所以这回都只煮了十多个安
So I only made about ten eggs.
# 嗯
okay.
# 那个茶叶蛋久不久（时不时）吃一回还是可以
It’s okay to have it once in a while.
# 多香噶
It tastes good.
# 嗯
yes.
# 我们这个茶叶蛋不能多吃
Don’t eat tea egg too much,
# 因为这个毕竟对身体不是特别好
it’s not good for health.
# 好啦 现在我们这个蛋已经煮熟了
Alright, the egg is hard-boiled already.
# 把它捞出来 过一下凉水
Put them in the cold water.
# 透一下凉水的话它就更好剥
It ’s better to peel it with cold water
# 好 现在我们稍微冰凉一下
Now we cold the egg a little bit.
# 轻轻地敲一下
Slightly knock it.
# 好了 现在我们重新加水
Done. Now we refill some water.
# 这一次加的水可以稍微多一点点
You can add more water this time.
# 然后放点这个香料
And put some spices.
# 丢2颗八角
Two star anises,
# 丢一小块桂皮
a small piece of cinnamon
# 我们四川喜欢吃辣椒
We love spice in Sichuan,
# 就放几个干辣椒进去
So put a few dried chili peppers.
# 再放两片香叶
two bay leaf,
# 然后加点老抽调色
and some dark soy sauce to make it looks good.
# 调色我们先搅一下 看一下这个颜色怎么样
We mixed it first to see the color.
# 可以了
That’s enough.
# 嗯 颜色没什么问题
Yes, it’s the right color.
# 好 现在我们来准备一下这个茶叶
Now let’s prepare the tea.
# 好了吗
Is it enough?
# 可以了可以了
That’s enough.
# 这里大概只有10克都不到的样子
There are about 10 grams of tea.
# 可以了
That’s good.
# 然后我们用这个开水 用八九十度的开水
Now we use boiling water, about 80 to 90 degrees.
# 给它泡一下 第一遍的不要
seak it in, throw away the first time’s water.
# 搅一下
mix it up.
# 你不盖着 第一轮它泡不到嘎
The flavor won’t come out if you don’t cover it.
# 一会儿的 就是第一遍这个水不要
It’s okay, we just don’t need the water from the first time.
# 好 现在可以了
Now, it’s okay.
# 把这个茶叶加进去
We put the tea into the pot.
# 好 最后我们来放点盐
Lastly, we add some salt.
# 盐的话可以稍微重一些
We can put more salt in it,
# 因为水也比较多嘛
because there’s more water.
# 最后我们来加点这个可乐
Lastly, we add some coke.
# 这个是上次做懒人排骨剩的是不
This is the leftover from cooking the pork ribs, right?
# 嗯
Yes.
# 好了嘛 这个电饭锅都满了
That’s enough, the pot is almost full.
# 好 稍微加一点
right, just adds a little bit.
# 所以我们这个就不用加糖了
So there is no need to add sugar.
# 可乐里面都有一点甜味了
Coke is already sweet.
# 然后给它盖上
Cover it up.
# 重新烧开
Reboli it.
# 现在这烧开了之后 继续让它煮一会儿
Now it’s boiling, let it keep boil for a bit.
# 煮完之后最重要的一个东西就是
the most important thing after boiling
# 让它浸泡 浸泡4个小时才更容易入味
is to let it soak for four hours, to get flavor penetration.
# 四伯爷
Uncle,
# 啷个嘛 还吃点可乐啊
What? Drink some coke?
# 啊
yes,
# 又在冒泡子了
It’s getting bubble.
# 哦哟
# 我喝这点
I will finish this.
# 好
Yeah,
# 诶呀 安逸
nice.
# 可以嘎
Good?
# 好喝
So good.
# 现在我们这个茶叶蛋已经在这个电饭锅里面
Now the egg has been put in the pot
# 用煨的方式 煮饭的方式
simmering
# 已经煮了40分钟了
for 40 minutes.
# 这个时候我先拿2个我们吃一下来试哈看哈
Let’s take two and try them first.
# 可以安
Alright.
# 这个颜色都出来了哒
The color changed
# 剩下的继续
leave the rest of them alone.
# 现在就把火关了 让它泡
Now turn off the heat, let them soak.
# 再泡几个小时
Soak for a few hours.
# 尝一哈看嘛四伯爷
Try a piece, uncle.
# 有点烫
A little bit hot.
# 诶呀 真的很烫
It’s really hot.
# 你看这样颜色都已经出来了
Look the color stick in.
# 你看我这个才安逸
Look at mine,
# 嗯
Right.
# 这个茶叶蛋就是现在还不是特别入味
The egg is not flavor penetration now.
# 好烫哦
It’s so hot.
# 我来给你弄
Let me help you.
# 转到一哈就给它逮（剥）开了
Peel it this way.
# 给它滚一哈 自己就掉了
Let it roll so the eggshell will get off.
# 是不是
Right?
# 我先尝哈看
Let me try it first.
# 烫
Hot.
# 等它冷哈都
Cool it down a little bit.
# 太烫了
too hot.
# 还可以
It’s quite ok.
# 但是中间现在还没有味道
The middle part is not flavor penetration, though.
# 很香
Smells so good.
# 闻起来已经有茶叶的香味
You can smell the tea flavor already.
# 已经有那个清香味了
It has a clear smell from tea.
# 但是说中间还没有入味
But the middle part is not flavored.
# 烫哦四伯爷
It’s hot, uncle.
# 少少的吃撒
Just try a little bit.
# 还没咋个入味
It’s not flavor penetrated yet.
# 嗯
yes.
# 再隔几个小时来吃差不多
It will get better after soaking for a couple of hours.
# 好 我们再等4个小时再来
Alright, Let’s wait for four more hours.
# 现在已经 大家可以看一下
Now, as you guys can see,
# 已经浸泡进去了
the eggs have soaked in.
# 慢慢来
Take it slowly.
# 嗯 不要掉
Don’t drop it.
# 现在我们这个鸡蛋 这个茶叶蛋
Now our tea egg,
# 可乐茶叶蛋已经放了好几个小时了
our coke tea eggs have been put for hours.
# 现在捞一个出来
Let’s get one out.
# 四伯爷你吃一个不
Uncle, you want to try one?
# 我不要
No...
# 你不要啊
You don’t want one?
# 不要了 刚才吃了饭安
No, just finished a meal.
# 要的
Right.
# 我们这个是早上开始做的
We made it this morning,
# 现在已经到下午2点钟了
Now it’s about 2 PM.
# 也应该入味了
It should get the flavor.
# 我来尝哈就晓得了
We will see after a taste.
# 好多个小时了嘛
It’s been a couple of hours.
# 你看 这个颜色的话就要比
Look, the color changed.
# 这个颜色就变得多了
The color changed darker
# 比上午更加要深一点
than the one in the morning.
# 嗯 入味了现在
It gets flavor penetration now.
# 现在比较入味
Now it’s flavorful.
# 不错不错
Nice.
# 这个蛋我们捞出来吃
When we want to eat it,
# 味道够了的时候就把蛋捞出来
We eat it when the egg gets flavor.
# 捞出来就可以了 不用再继续泡了
Just take them out, no need for soaking.
# 然后这个汤汁的话
And for the gravy,
# 嗯 还可以卤一次
We can use it to make the tea egg again.
# 最好就不要超过3次
But no more than three times.
# 超过3次的话这个味道就不香了
If it uses more than three time, it’s not flavored anymore.
# 但这个可能放不得哦噶
But the gravy can’t last o]long.
# 放不到好久
It doesn’t last long.
# 三两天可以放在冰箱头
You can put it in the refrigerator for about two or three days.
# 最好是当天做当天吃
The best way is to finish it by the day.
# 是整多了的话
If you made more,
# 煮多了的话
if you cooked more,
# 放在保鲜室里头可能保一两天没得问题的哈
You can put it in the refrigerator for about two or three days.
# 一两天没得问题的
the egg could last for one to two days.
# 好了 大家如果是想吃的话可以尝试一下
Alright, if you guys want to eat tea egg, you can try this method.
# 特别的简单
It’s very simple.
# 就跟懒人排骨一样
Just like the easy pork rib.
# 也不用加太多的东西
And you don’t need to add too much material.
# 本期视频就到这里 拜拜
That’s it for today’s video, bye-bye.
# 拜拜
Bye-bye.
# 真的可以你不要笑
It could work, don’t laugh.
# 吃一个嘛
Want to try one?
# 我刚才吃了饭
I just ate.